Leon J. Galloway Collection
Leon J. Galloway Collection
1711-1962
Galloway, Leon J.
5 linear ft.
Collection created by Leon Galloway of Hicksville, New York, presumably based on his personal interests. Correspondence of military members of the Confederate States of America and Civil War currency. Contracts, land surveys, photo albums, and books about the Hicksite Quakers. Correspondence of the Saunders family.
2727982
Biographical History
Leon J. Galloway was the principal of Hicksville High School in Hicksville, New York, a hamlet within the town of Oyster Bay on Long Island. He was a member of the Kiwanis Club in 1937 and the president of the club in 1942. He was also a Quaker.
Elias Hicks (1748-1830) was originally a member of the Society of Friends (Quakers) in Philadelphia. In the 1820s the group split, partially (though not entirely) over some of Hicks' views including denial of the virgin birth and emphasis on "the light within" over the literal text of the Bible. Followers of Hicks, among whom was Walt Whitman, were known as "Hicksites."
Limited information is available on the Saunders Family. William and Susan Saunders moved their family from London, England to Rochester, New York in 1850. The family members appearing in the collection are William Tyrie Saunders; his father William and mother Susan; his wife Elizabeth; his sisters Elizabeth and Alice; and brothers Charles, Frank, Herbert, and Phillip. In 1851, William Tyrie was a 20 year old engraver-on-wood apprentice in London. He stayed in London while his family moved to America. On 1 November 1851, he married Elizabeth Mary Crews at the parish church of St. Giles-in-the-Fields, London and eventually had six children with Elizabeth. William Tyrie's wood engraving business moved periodically around Lincolns Inn Fields within the Holborn neighborhood of London. William Tyrie died 15 March 1886 at the age of 55, Elizabeth followed her husband 3 May 1905 at the age of 71.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Leon J. Galloway Collection consists of material relating to the Confederate States of America, the Hicksite Quakers, the Saunders family, and some miscellaneous items.
Confederate States of America series includes correspondence from important individuals within the Confederacy, such as Jefferson Davis, Daniel Ruggles, Fitzhugh Lee, Pierre G.T. Beauregard, and many others. The series also includes currency from all states within the Confederacy, Galloway's collected notes on this series, portraits, printed material, and war bonds.
Hicksite Quakers consists of contracts between individuals and land surveys of Hicksville, New York; a letter by Elias Hicks to William B Trish; a handwritten manuscript by David Seaman; photo albums of Quakers with handwritten notes of individuals; and a book describing the Hicksite Quakers and their doctrines.
Within the Saunders family series are letters from William Tyrie Saunders and his family: his father William and mother Susan; his wife Elizabeth; his sisters Elizabeth and Alice; and brothers Charles, Frank, Herbert, and Phillip.
Miscellaneous series is divided into correspondence and memorabilia. Within correspondence are letters directed to Galloway, to the Middletown Monthly Meeting in Bucks County, Pennsylvania; from the executive chamber for the state of New York; and to the headmaster of the Friends Academy in Locust Valley, New York. In memborabilia, there are autograph books of Dr. Theron Wendell Kilmer and Fredrick Bulkley Tuttle. Kilmer was the nephew of Tuttle. Also, there are two first day of issue stamps.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is arranged alphabetically by title, type, or topic, and within each folder chronologically.
Related Material
has a substantial amount of material in both manuscript and rare books holdings relating to Quakers and other mid-nineteenth century religious movements. Please refer to to locate printed/cataloged material and to for a listing of manuscript material.
Subject and Genre Headings
Religion and philosophy; Civil War (U.S.); Beauregard, G. T. (Gustave Toutant), 1818-1893.; Belknap, William W. (William Worth), 1829-1890.; Benjamin, J. P. (Judah Philip), 1811-1884.; Blaine, James Gillespie, 1830-1893.; Bradley, Joseph H. (Joseph Habersham), 1802-1887.; Bragg, Braxton, 1817-1876.; Browne, William M. (William Montague), 1823-1883.; Davis, Jefferson, 1808-1889.; Early, Jubal Anderson, 1816-1894.; Fish, Hamilton, 1808-1893.; Hampton, Wade, 1818-1902.; Hardee, William Joseph, 1815-1873.; Hill, D. H. (Daniel Harvey), 1821-1889.; Lamar, L. Q. C. (Lucius Quintus Cincinnatus), 1825-1893.; Lee, Fitzhugh, 1835-1905.; Lee, Stephen D. (Stephen Dill), 1833-1908.; Longstreet, James, 1821-1904.; Mallory, Stephen R. (Stephen Russell), 1813-1873.; McLaws, Lafayette, 1821-1897.; Ruggles, Daniel, 1810-1897.; Seward, William H. (William Henry), 1801-1872.; Sherman, John, 1823-1900.; Stephens, Alexander H. (Alexander Hamilton), 1812-1883.; Smith, Gerrit, 1797-1874.; Taylor, Richard, 1826-1879.; Hicks, Elias, 1748-1830.; Seaman family.; Hicks family.; Willis family.; Townsend family.; Doty family.; Mott family.; Aldridge family.; Saunders family.; Hicksites -- United States -- History.; Confederate States of America.; Society of Friends.; Quakers.; United States -- Church history -- 19th century.; Lincoln's Inn Fields (London, England); Hicksville (N.Y.); Oyster Bay (N.Y.); Jericho (Nassau County, N.Y.); Westbury (Nassau County, N.Y.); Photographs.; Photograph albums.; Paper money.; Autograph albums.; Correspondence.; Postage stamps.; Contracts.; Land surveys.; Marriage certificates.; Wills.; Manuscripts (documents); War bonds.; Engravings (prints)
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advance notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Leon J. Galloway, 1978.
Inventory
- Confederate States of America
  - Donor notes, Galloway's notes on the Confederate States of America series (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - Beauregard, Pierre G.T., 1870 (Box 1)
    - Belknap, William W., 1884 (Box 1)
    - Benjamin, Judah Philip, 1863 (Box 1)
    - Blaine, James Gillespie, 1889 (Box 1)
    - Bradley, Joseph H., 1861-1866 (Box 1)
    - Bragg, Braxton, 1864 (Box 1)
    - Browne, William Montague, 1877 (Box 1)
    - Davis, Jefferson, 1854; 1863,; 1880,; 1885-1886,; 1889-1890 (Box 1)
    - Early, Jubal, 1872 (Box 1)
    - Fish, Hamilton, 1869-1870 (Box 1)
    - Hampton, Wade, 1882 (Box 1)
    - Hardee, William Joseph, 1865 (Box 1)
    - Hill, Daniel Harvey, 1887 (Box 1)
    - Kimmel, Manning Marius, 1862 (Box 1)
    - Lamar, Lucius Quintus Cincinnatus, 1886 (Box 1)
    - Lee, Fitzhugh, 1879; 1886,; 1892 (Box 1)
    - Lee, Stephen Dill, 1885; 1889 (Box 1)
    - Longstreet, James, 1857; 1884 (Box 1)
    - Mallory, Stephen Russell, undated (Box 1)
    - McLaws, Lafayette, 1888 (Box 1)
    - Ruggles, Daniel, 1862; 1885 (Box 1)
    - Schurz, Carl Christian, 1880 (Box 1)
    - Seward, William Henry, 1855 (Box 1)
    - Sherman, John, 1865 (Box 1)
    - Stephens, Alexander, 1850; 1882 (Box 1)
    - Taylor, Richard, 1865 (Box 1)
    - Welle, Gideon, 1836 (Box 1)
    - Confederate States of America, miscellaneous, 1848-1854; 1857-1868,; 1879,; 1882,; 1885-1892,; 1900-1901,; 1905,; 1908; correspondence from and to Confederate military members; 4 folders (Box 1)
    - Other
      - Smith, Gerrit, 1870 (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous, 1865; 1869; includes John Bright; Clinton DeWitt; Wendell Phillips; Prince Philippe of Orleans, Count of Paris; and John Russell, 1st Earl Russell (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous, 1859-1863; 1866; unidentified individuals (Box 1)
  - Currency
    - Alabama, 1863-1864 (Oversize 6)
    - Arkansas, 1862 (Oversize 6)
    - Florida, 1862-1864 (Oversize 6)
    - Georgia, 1831; 1849,; 1854-1865, (Oversize 6)
    - Kentucky, 1864 (Oversize 6)
    - Louisiana, 1834; 1839,; 1842,; 1862-1864 (Oversize 6)
    - Mississippi, 1862 (Oversize 6)
    - Missouri, 1862 (Oversize 6)
    - North Carolina, 1861; 1863-1867, (Oversize 6)
    - South Carolina, 1856; 1861-1863,; 1867,; 1872 (Oversize 6)
    - Tennessee, 1862-1863 (Oversize 6)
    - Texas, 1861-1862 (Oversize 6)
    - Virginia, 1850; 1861-1862 (Oversize 6)
    - Eastman College, 2 items: one cent and three cent notes (Box 1)
    - Confederate States of America, 1862-1864 (Oversize 6)
    - Confederate States of America, 1862-1864 (Oversize 7)
    - Confederate States of America, 1862-1864; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - United States of America, 1845; 1862,; 1882,; 1899,; 1908,; 1914,; 1917,; 1923,; 1928,; 1935,; 1953,; 1957 (Box 2)
    - Dominion of Canada, 1878 (Box 2)
  - Portraits
    - Engravings (Box 2)
    - Photographs (Box 2)
  - Printed material, 1896-1898 (Box 2)
  - War bonds, 1864-1865 (Box 2)
  - War bonds, 1836-1864 (Oversize 5)
- Hicksite Quakers
  - A book of records of the division of the plain land by Robert Williams, 1948; photostatic reproduction of the original division records of the plain purchase of 1648 (Oversize 4)
  - Contracts, 1715-1716; 1731,; 1744-1748,; 1751,; 1764-1769,; 1778-1780,; 1784,; 1789-1799, (Oversize 5)
  - Contracts, 1801-1806; 1809-1814,; 1817,; 1821-1822,; 1826-1828,; 1831-1838,; 1841-1844,; 1852-1855,; 1869 (Oversize 5)
  - David Seaman's manuscript, 1787 (Box 2)
  - Hicks, Elias
    - Correspondence, 1820 (Box 2)
    - Marriage certificate, 1771 (Oversize 5)
  - The Hicksite Quakers and Their Doctrines by James M. DeGarmo, 1895; history and overview of the Hicksite Quakers and their beliefs (Box 2)
  - Land surveys, 1711-1714; 1717,; 1768,; 1780,; 1793,; 1806,; 1812,; 1822-1824,; 1851,; 1864 (Oversize 5)
  - Memorial of Samuel Hicks Seaman and His Wife Hannah Richardson Husband compiled by Mary Thomas Seaman, 1927; extensive family genealogy of predominantly Hicksite Quakers (Box 2)
  - Photo album, undated; "To Mother from Lottie and Amie" (Oversize 1)
  - Photo albums, undated; 2 volumes (Oversize 3)
  - Miscellaneous, 1802; 1806,; 1815; bill of sale, sermon notes, Hannah Tredwell's will, poem by Matthew Green, and late 19th century or early 20th century map of Hicksville (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous, 1832; 1844; list of land sales, unknown contract, blank contract form. (Oversize 5)
- Saunders family
  - Correspondence, 1850-1865; 1868; undated; 3 folders (Box 3)
- Miscellaneous
  - Autograph book, Theron Wendell Kilmer, 1888 (Box 3)
  - Autograph book, Fredrick Bulkley Tuttle, undated (Oversize 2)
  - Correspondence, 1837; 1909,; 1937,; 1944,; 1953,; 1962 (Box 3)
  - Stamps, 1965-1966 (Box 3)